MICHAEL FARES

703-244-0370 | mjfares@gmail.com

https://github.com/Michael-Fares https://michaelfares.netlify.app https://michael-fares.medium.com

FRONTEND WEB DEVELOPER | EDUCATOR

I'm a JavaScript developer with a versatile skill set in frontend / full stack technologies and best practices. I'm also an award winning educator with 10+ years of university teaching experience. My goal is to use my skills to build outstanding digital learning platforms, making education equitable for 21st century learners everywhere.

Core Competencies

Frontend Development • Backend Development • Unit Testing • Agile Workflow • Relational Databases • SEO • Continuous Integration and Deployment • Web Accessibility • Curriculum Design • Educational Technology • Teaching/Higher Education • Research/Data Analysis • Fluent in Arabic

Technical Skills

HTML • CSS • Bootstrap • JavaScript • React • Redux • MaterialUI • Chart.js • Recharts.js • Node • NPM • Express • REST API • Git • Github • Google Cloud (GCP) • Heroku • Netlify • MySQL • AWS • ESLint

EXPERIENCE

Zollege, Austin, TX

Jan 2022 - Present **Software Developer**

I work closely with a team of fellow developers to plan, design, build and integrate new full stack web applications and features into various digital learning platforms.

- Whiteboard and implement robust frontend user interfaces to deliver educational content to students
- Identify and collaboratively solve problems related to frontend-backend integration

University of Houston, Houston, TX

Aug 2012 - Present

Professor of Arabic

I teach Arabic as a second language to hundreds of college students from many backgrounds, and work on multiple administrative teams to deliver extracurricular offerings including community internships, study abroad, and public cultural events.

- Design, implement, and maintain original Arabic language curriculum content for all levels
- Multiple published articles and public talks on Arabic language, culture, translation and best teaching practices.
- Faculty Teaching Excellence Award, 2020
- Outstanding Mentorship Award, 2020

Greenhill School, Dallas, TX

Aug 2009 - June 2010

Middle School Teacher

- Created and taught original lesson plans for 5th graders in all subjects.
- Supervised students during after school programs and planned activities to ensure their learning and fun.
- Communicated regularly with parents about students' progress and learning needs.

EDUCATION

Austin Coding Academy Bootcamp

Full Stack Web Development | December 2021

University of Texas at Austin

MA, Arabic Language | May 2012